Finding Aid for General Clinical Research Center (University of Michigan) publications 1961-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
General Clinical Research Center (University of Michigan) publications 1961-1993
University of Michigan. General Clinical Research Center.
Reprints of medical journal articles describing medical cases and treatment protocols based upon clinical trials in the University of Michigan General Clinical Research Center.
02100 Bimu C500 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
11 linear feet
Publications are received periodically from the General Clinical Research Center (donor # 7274 ).
The records are open for research.
The University Hospitals have a long tradition of supplying research beds for detailed patient studies. In accordance with this tradition, in 1959, when renovations of University Hospital vacated a large amount of space on the ground floor, a faculty committee recommended that the space be used for research beds. In June 1959 the United States Congress recommended to the National Institutes of Health (NIH) that it fund the establishment of research bed facilities in academic institutions throughout the country. This combination of faculty recommendation and Congressional will led to the establishment of a NIH-funded, Clinical Research Center at University Hospital in May 1962.
Equipped with 16 inpatient beds and 8 outpatient beds, the Center represents an unusually stable environment where a specially trained nursing and dietetic staff, supported by dedicated laboratory facilities, can obtain precise control of clinical procedures and carefully observed patient reaction. To make use of the facility, a researcher must submit a written protocol explaining the nature of the experiment, its specific methodology and the likely results. The Center's Operating Subcommittee meets regularly to consider the protocols, as well as establish priorities and oversee the Center's daily operations. Overall responsibility for the Center's activities resides with the Policy Committee.
Subsequent grants from the NIH have allowed the Center to continue in operation for over thirty years. Copies of protocols are sent to NIH as part of the competing renewal grant report to NIH each year. The Center must submit a non-competing grant report to NIH each year. In 1992 the name of the Center was changed to General Clinical Research Center.
During 1999, over 150 individual adult and pediatric research studies were active at the Center, involving collaborations between over 400 investigators resulting in a total of 1828 GCRC-funded and 153 industry-sponsored inpatient days, and 3134 GCRC-funded outpatient visits. Some areas of research included: Alzheimer's, AIDS, cancer, depression, dermatology, diabetes, epilepsy, gene therapy, growth disorders, heart disease, hypertension, intestinal hormones, kidney disease, menopause, and obesity.
The General Clinical Research Center Publications (11 linear feet) are comprised of a single series: Unit Publications. The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the General Clinical Research Center. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. General Clinical Research Center.
Genre/Form:
Reprints.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series is made up of forty-eight bound volumes covering the period from 1961 to 1993. Entitled Clinical Research Unit Publications, these volumes are a series of reprints from various medical journals describing medical cases and treatment protocols based upon clinical trials in the University of Michigan General Clinical Research Center. Each volume is arranged alphabetically by the first author listed on the title page of the reprint. There is a table of contents for each volume which has been reproduced for the researcher's convenience and appended to the finding aid. The first volume covers the period from 1961 through 1966. After that there was usually one volume of reprints for each year. Beginning in the year 1986-1987 there are at least three bound volumes for each year.
  - Clinical Research Unit Publications
    - Vols. 1-4 1961-1971, 5 volumes (Box 1)
    - Vols. 5-9 1972-1978, 5 volumes (Box 2)
    - Vols. 10-13 1979-1982, 5 volumes (Box 3)
    - Vols. 14-16 1982-1985, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - Vols. 17-18 1985-1987, 4 volumes (Box 5)
    - Vol. 19 1987-1988, 3 volumes (Box 6)
    - Vol. 20 1988-1989, 4 volumes (Box 7)
    - Vol. 21 1989-1990, 3 volumes (Box 8)
    - Vol. 22 1990-1991, 4 volumes (Box 9)
    - Vol. 23 1991-1992, 1 volumes (Box 9)
    - Vol. 23 1991-1992, 4 volumes (Box 10)
    - Vol. 24 1992-1993, 1 volumes (Box 10)
    - Vol. 24 1992-1993, 6 volumes (Box 11)